In today's video we're going to do
some basic questions that I get asked
all the time about ice cream making
problems and how you can resolve them.
So I get asked so many questions on all my videos
about why is my ice cream doing this, why is my
ice cream doing that, and these are questions
generally from people that have adjusted a recipe,
they've adjusted a scientifically calculated
and balanced ice cream or sorbet recipe and
they wonder why it goes wrong. So we're going
to go through how many.... 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10
we're going to go through 10 basic problems and
then a few terminology as well. These questions
come up all the time and hopefully they'll help
you transform your homemade ice cream or sorbet.
So the first question we're going to
tackle is: Why is my ice cream too hard?
When ice cream goes too hard in the freezer,
too hard to scoop, too hard to spoon and eat,
that is generally down to one of two things.
Number one is there's not enough sugar in there
and number two is there's way too much fat. When
you make ice cream, there is a specific amount
of sugar required to get the texture that you're
after. It's the same if you use a sugar substitute
as well so it it's a balance of getting the right
amount of freezing depression vs your recipe and
this is where terms like POD and PAC come in. POD
is the amount of sweetness, PAC is how hard it
freezes, so if you use a perfectly balanced recipe
and you've balanced it so that it is scoopable
straight from your freezer it means the the amount
of sugar and or sugar substitute is perfect for
your recipe and the amount of solids that you
have in there. If you start playing with that,
let's say you use sugar and you think actually
I don't want to use that much sugar because
to me that's too much, you start taking that
Sugar out, let's say you take half your sugar out
of your ice cream recipe you've removed half the
solids and you've subtracted half of the freezing
point depression ingredient from your ice cream
which means it's going to go much much harder in
your freezer. So you need to understand what the
ingredients do and their effect on your ice cream.
Question number two is: My ice cream
is too soft or it won't freeze at all?
Again this actually is exactly the polar opposite
to the last question, this is you've got too much
sugar and or you've affected the freezing point
too much. So if you use something like Xylitol
which has a strong effect on the freezing point or
Erythritol, which is awful in ice cream, that has
a really strong effect on a freezing point. If you
use too much of these and you cook your recipe and
you put it in a freezer for a ninja creamy and
it doesn't freeze and or you put it in your ice
cream machine and it doesn't churn, it's because
you've brought the freezing point down so low that
your freezer can't freeze it, that your ice cream
machine can't freeze it. The walls of an ice cream
machine like a standard home churning machine
get down to about minus 20°C - 25°C depending
on the machine so you have to really go some to
stop it freezing. Your standard freezer at home
is somewhere around -17°C minus 18°C again that's
actually surprisingly easy to get it below that
point, you think "okay I'm going to use a sugar
substitute" this recipe calls for 150g of table
sugar I'll add 150g of Erthritol, it it won't
freeze. It will have a freezing point of about
-30°C so it won't freeze at all and you you know
when when people come on and say "oh my my ice
cream didn't freeze your recipe is rubbish"
what did you.... my first question is what
did you change, because they change something
and here we come with the "oh I didn't want to
use sugar I want to use Erthritol" you can't make
these drastic changes to recipes, it's the same
for baking as well, you can't just substitute
something for something else and expect it to
be the same. You need to understand what they do.
Question number three is: My ice cream is too icy?
Ice crystals form for a couple of reasons,
ice cream itself is a balance of ice crystals,
air bubbles and fat that that's what creates ice
cream with the right size ice crystals the right
amount of air Incorporated and the right amount
of fat you get this perfect texture. When your
ice cream is too icy it means your ice crystals
have been allowed to increase in size more than
we would like. That happens for a few reasons,
one is there's not enough sugar to to counter that
freezing process number two is the ingredients
like to recrystallize after you've made the ice
cream and number three is you haven't stabilized
any of that free water so if you you if you make
an ice cream and it has 60% water content, that
water needs to be stabilized in a couple of ways
one is either you can create a sugar syrup and
stabilize the water with the sugar and that will
help reduce the freezing point of your water and
slow the Ice Crystal formation which will then in
turn make the Ice Crystal smaller or you stabilize
it with something like Guar gum, Xanthan gum,
Tara gum any of those you know, Locust bean gum,
caraggenan all these all these stabilizers what
they do is they bond to the water and create
a more viscous liquid which then reduces the
Ice Crystal formation. Another reason ice crystals
form is the amount of time it takes to churn your
ice cream, in a traditional machine if you have
a like a freezer bowl one where you put it in
the freezer for 24 hours and bring it out, they
are historically much slower at churning than a
high-end compressor machine. The slower the churn
the larger the ice crystals get so if you were to
take my musso, which is one I use on the videos
here, that will churn in about 12 to 15 minutes
depending on the recipe if you take a freezer bowl
version it might take 20 to 25 minutes your ice
crystals are going to be larger than they are
in mine. There's nothing we can do about that,
by balancing the recipe to suit your equipment
is the best way to combat that, so if you know
that your ice cream machine churns slow you can
reduce the sugar ever so slightly and that makes
it freeze quicker because it has a slightly higher
freezing point I also recommend it looking into
using stabilizers Gura gum, Xanthan gum you
know Tara gum, they're excellent even if you
don't look at any of the others and you don't look
at combining them those three are really really
good for making your ice cream much much better.
The next question is: My ice cream is not sweet
enough? this generally comes from people that do
"no sugar zero sugar low sugar" recipes the sugar
substitutes generally are not as sweet as sugar
and that is the POD, POD that is what that means
it's sweetness equivalency essentially compared to
sucrose so Allulose is like 70% as sweet as table
sugar xylitol is about 65 to 70% as sweet as table
sugar all these kind of things when you start
using them in recipes and your ice cream isn't
sweet enough to taste you can boost the sweetness
using something like Stevia where you really only
need like three drops or four drops depending on
the size of your recipe to increase the sweetness
or apparent sweetness, perceived sweetness to a
level that's in line with traditional table sugar.
Next question is: My ice cream gets icy after a
couple of days? this happens again for a few
reasons mainly one of two. One is that you
continually open your freezer, open and close,
open and close, what you're doing is you're
thawing your ice cream ever so slightly when you
open it because you're removing all that cold air
and then you are closing it and it's refreezing
again, you create that freeze thaw cycle and every
every time you freeze and thaw, freeze and thaw,
the ice crystals will increase in size. If you
have a frost-free freezer then that most of the
time, every night those things go up to a certain
temperature to melt the ice and then they freeze
back down that will have a huge impact on your ice
cream. I hate frost free fridge freezers for that
reason they destroy the texture of your ice cream
and sorbet. And generally the other reason is
stabilization there's too much free water in there
and as an Ice Crystal starts to form over time it
will just get bigger and bigger and bigger because
there's too much unprocessed water in a recipe
and that's why we need to look at stabilizing that
water, thicken it so that it doesn't get larger
and larger in size and stays luscious, silky
and smooth like the ice cream that we all enjoy.
The next question is: Crumbly texture to my ice
cream? this is usually caused by too high solids,
it can also be caused by too high milk solids you
can get a crumbly texture in two different ways
one when you go and scoop it it doesn't scoop
a nice smooth creamy ball, it breaks apart
as you scoop it, that's generally too high
solids. If your ice cream has a sandy kind of
texture, that is generally caused by too high
milk solids so you need to balance your recipe
and adjust it to suit the texture that you want.
Nobody likes sandy textured ice cream so don't
give me a load of BS " that's how you like it"
Next question is: My ice cream melts too fast?
melting ice cream ..... ice cream melts, it's
made of ice.... ice melts..... if it's melting too
fast it's because there's too much free water in
there the moment it starts to melt it would just
exponentially get worse. Deal with the excess
water and your ice cream won't melt as fast. Also
look at using a stabilizer that will increase the
viscosity of the any free water in your recipe
that will also slow the melt down as well.
Next question is: My ice cream doesn't melt
at all? that means you've used way too much
stabilizer and you are holding,
in a very strange gelatinous mass,
all the air which can't escape so reduce your
stabilizer use and you will lose that problem.
The final texture question or issue question
is: A gummy texture? and this is also caused
by too much stabilizer Xanthan gum is
terrible for causing a gummy texture,
I don't really like using Xanthan gum a lot
because you can't can't very successfully
stabilize a decent amount of water without
it going gummy so I much prefer Guar gum if
I'm going to use a single process stabilizer
or a cold process single stabilizer Tara gum
is infinitely better than both of them so I
recommend you try a different stabilizer if
that's the common problem that you're having.
Gelato will use a lot more stabilizer than ice
cream will because there's a lot more
free water because there's lower fat.
The next section is common ice cream terms
and the first one everyone always ask me is:
What is overrun? overrun simply means
the amount of air incorporated into an
ice cream. Store bought ice cream from the
supermarket can have anywhere in excess of
100 to 150% overrun there is a legal amount
in in the USA and most people don't seem
to abide by that unfortunately but the
lighter a tub of ice cream is the more
air that's incorporated into it so you're
paying more especially for keto low sugar
,no sugar recipes all of those... Halo it weighs
nothing I did a video on this you know a month
or two ago um where I compared the weight of a
tub of Ben & Jerry's to a tub of Halo and you
it's 50% more overrun than a standard tub of
Ben & Jerry's so we're looking at 100% overrun
and that is how they get past calories as well
by increasing the air means they're reducing
the calories per tub. Makes everything sound much
nicer, in reality you're just paying more for air.
What is the term term SMP? SMP simply stands
for "skim milk powder" so that is zero fat
milk powder or 0.1% fat milk powder. You can
get away with 1% milk powder but don't use
whole milk powder if you can help, it has a
really weird taste. What we're trying to do
with skim milk powder is increase the milk
solids without increasing the fat content.
What is an ice cream stabilizer? an ice
cream stabilizer is simply an additional
ingredient that helps us increase the
viscosity of our ice cream or sorbet,
any free water and improves the texture and
longevity of the ice cream that we make.
What is the difference between ice
cream and gelato? ice cream and gelato,
the term gelato means Frozen and or
Ice cream depending on who you ask,
but essentially gelato is lower fat higher
sugar ice cream and ice cream, which is
a generalized term for American ice cream, is
higher fat lower sugar. That's the difference,
gelato generally has a slightly less overrun
than American ice cream but as most home ice
cream machines don't have any control over that I
wouldn't worry about it. The way to think about it
is gelato has lower fat usually between 5 and 8%
fat and American ice cream has somewhere between
11 and 18% fat there are some excellent ice
creams out there with over 18% fat and there are
some excellent ice creams in between that band
from 8 to 11% so take it with a pinch of salt.
Why do you age your ice cream base? some
ice creams have a lot of complex flavors
that will come out and improve when you
age and that is literally just leaving
the base in the refrigerator for 24 hours to
allow those flavor elements to come out and
bond together to create something really
unique. Chocolate is a classic for it,
cocoa should be bloomed anyway and
that's why we cook our chocolate
bases but it also improves in flavor
when we age them in the refrigerator.
What is butter fat and or milk fat? that is
simply a term used for the amount of fat that
is contained in Dairy, Milk, cream it's all got
different amounts of fat in it so you know your
Ultra skimmed milk is you know basically 0.1%
fat in... this is the UK semi skimmed milk
is around 1.8 to 2% fat, whole milk is around
3% to 3.5% fat then you've got 3% in you know
here in Canada you got your whole milk which
is about 3.25% you've got your 2% milk which
is the equivalent of semi skimmed, these are all
just numbers, the amounts of fat in that dairy,
cream is the same. Double cream in the UK is
50% milk fat/butter fat, same term same thing,
whipping cream here is about 33 to 36% milk
fat/butter fat depending on which one you buy
that is what that term is. It's the same if you
hear someone say butter fat they mean milk fat,
if you hear someone say milk fat
they mean butter fat.... same thing.
Finally eggs versus stabilizers? the age old
question what ice cream is better custard based or
non- custard based! I don't know, I can't judge,
I personally don't like using eggs that much in
ice cream. I find it wasteful because you have
to find something to do with the egg whites and
in the modern terms and days now, we have ways of
doing the same thing that an egg yolk would do. An
egg yolk increases the fat % ever so slightly,
I mean it's a tiny amount too but essentially
you should consider egg yolks to be emulsifier.
So the Lecithin within an egg yolk is what the
is beneficial part to a recipe, a custard
recipe it helps to thicken and or bond water
and fat molecules together to create a better
emulsion. If you don't want to use eggs and
you want to do the same thing then you can just
buy lecithin in powder or liquid form. I'm going
to go into emulsifiers in more detail in up and
coming videos and I'm also going to show you how
best to make custard based ice creams. I have had
some amazing custard based ice creams I've also
had some amazing eggless ice creams, I've also had
some amazing custard-based ice creams that don't
use eggs!..... so you can achieve whatever you
want to achieve however you want to achieve it,
just do what's right for you. If you want to
make a custard version of an ice cream that
I put on my channel then put some egg yolks in
there, it won't make any difference to the fat
content really all you're doing is using that
to thicken the base and replace the stabilizer.
Well I hope that helped cover a few basic
questions that you might have on your ice cream
journey, we got a lot of new subscribers to the
channel so I thought it might be beneficial to go
through some of those basic questions that I take
for granted and a lot of my long-term subscribers
will take for granted too. These are terms that
will come up time and time and time again, once
you realize that you have a perfect balanced set
of ingredients available to use for your homemade
ice cream your life will be so much easier.
You don't have to stress about worrying about
ice crystals, you'll never have that problem again
but if you are unsure about anything, feel free to
chime in in the comments, if I can't answer, some
of my long-term subscribers will. We've got some
excellent ice cream makers here following along,
if you're new ....welcome! You are about to embark
on a journey that is going improve your homemade
ice cream and sorbet to a whole other level.
Anyway thanks very much for watching, don't forget
to like and subscribe and I'll see you next time
[Music]